Clive Davis Papers ARC.0009
Library and Archives
Clive Davis Correspondence
Bulk, 1990-2000
1963-2001 and undated
ARC.0009
Library and Archives
0.417 Linear feet 1 Hollinger box
The Clive Davis Papers consist of correspondence between Clive Davis and various Arista and RCA recording artists and executives, spanning the years 1963 to 2001. In the correspondence, Davis and the artists discuss songs, lyrics, albums, and videos, as well as critical reception of the artists’ work, touring arrangements, and record deals and contracts. There are handwritten notes from several of the artists, including Aretha Franklin, Carlos Santana, Kenny G., Barry Manilow, and Carly Simon. The collection highlights a sample of late 20th century American popular music, provides perspective on the artistic decisions and business practices of the sound recording industry during that period, and illustrates the relationships between recording artists and executives. The Clive Davis Papers are arranged alphabetically by artist name, with a folder of miscellaneous correspondence and clippings at the end.
Biography
1934 Born in Brooklyn, NY
1960 Goes to work for Columbia Records as a contract lawyer
1967 Becomes president of Columbia Records
1967 June Attends Monterey Pop Festival
1973 Fired from Columbia Records
1974 Founds Arista Records
2000 Inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame
2003 Becomes president of RCA Music Group
A Harvard Law School graduate, Clive Davis joined the CBS Records Division as a contract lawyer in 1960. A savvy negotiator, Davis quickly gained the attention of his superiors and within a few short years had earned the top spot at Columbia Records. After attending the Monterey International Pop Festival in June 1967, Davis saw the monumental impact of rock music on society – and its enormous moneymaking potential. Shortly afterwards, he signed Big Brother and the Holding Company (featuring Janis Joplin) to Columbia, following with some of the biggest acts of the era, including Blood Sweat & Tears, Aerosmith, Billy Joel, and Bruce Springsteen. Davis was fired for misuse of company funds in 1973, but in 1974 founded Arista Records, where he ushered in a new era of pop music through the likes of Whitney Houston, Sarah McLachlan, Alan Jackson and Sean “Puffy” Combs.
Sources
"Clive Davis Biography." Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum. http://rockhall.com/inductees/clive-davis/bio/
Kurutz, Steve. "Clive Davis." All Music Guide. http://www.allmusic.com/cg/amg.dll?p=amg&sql=11:dvfrxq85ld6e~T1
Provenance
The Clive Davis Papers were received by the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame Foundation, Inc. as a gift from X on X.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights form before using this collection. Please contact reference staff before visiting the Library and Archives to use this collection.
Ace of Base (Musical group); Arista (Firm); Cox, Deborah, 1974-; Davis, Clive; Dayne, Taylor; Diddy, 1969-; Dido, 1971-; Franklin, Aretha; G., Kenny; Grateful Dead (Musical group); Houston, Whitney; LaFace Records.; Lennox, Annie; Manilow, Barry; McLachlan, Sarah; No Mercy (Musical group); Ostin, Mo, 1927-; Prince; Santana (Musical group); Simon, Carly; Sinatra, Frank, 1915-1998; Smith, Patti; Record labels.; Rock music.; Sound recording executives and producers.; Sound recording industry.
- Ace of Base, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Combs, Sean, 1995-2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Cox, Deborah, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Dayne, Taylor, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Dido, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Franklin, Aretha, 1979-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Grateful Dead, 1976-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Houston, Whitney, 1985-2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Kenny G, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- LaFace, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Lennox, Annie, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- McLachlan, Sarah, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- No Mercy, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Manilow, Barry, 1981-1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Ostin, Mo, 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Prince, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Santana, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Simon, Carly, 1998-2000 and undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Sinatra, Frank, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Smith, Patti, 1975-1994 and undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1990-2001 and undated (Box 1, Folder 21)